<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>de.penguincitizen.penguincitizen</id>

  <name>Penguin Citizen</name>
  <summary>Star Citizen launch manager for Linux</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="de">Star-Citizen-Launcher für Linux</summary>

  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>

  <developer id="de.penguincitizen">
    <name>Penguin Citizen Project</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Penguin Citizen is a desktop application that makes it easy to install,
      configure, and launch Star Citizen on Linux via Wine and Proton. It
      manages Wine and Proton runners, Wine prefixes, DXVK builds, and Star
      Citizen environment files (LIVE, PTU, EPTU, HOTFIX) in one place.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="de">
      Penguin Citizen ist eine Desktop-Anwendung, die das Installieren,
      Konfigurieren und Starten von Star Citizen unter Linux über Wine und
      Proton vereinfacht. Sie verwaltet Wine- und Proton-Runner, Wine-Prefixes,
      DXVK-Builds und Star-Citizen-Umgebungen (LIVE, PTU, EPTU, HOTFIX) an
      einer zentralen Stelle.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>One-click installation of the RSI Launcher inside a managed Wine prefix</li>
      <li>Built-in Wine/Proton runner manager with downloads from GitHub releases</li>
      <li>Visual editor for USER.cfg, attributes.xml and actionmaps.xml with diff against the live game state</li>
      <li>Joystick and gamepad binding editor with per-axis tuning (deadzone, saturation, exponent, invert)</li>
      <li>Shader-cache management for SC and DXVK</li>
      <li>German localization installer (Hybrid and Full variants) with optional Blueprint integration</li>
      <li>Data.p4k recycling between environments via copy, move, or symlink</li>
      <li>Linux compatibility checks with guided fixes for vm.max_map_count and file-max limits</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">de.penguincitizen.penguincitizen.desktop</launchable>

  <url type="homepage">https://penguincitizen.de</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/TomRhodan/penguin-citizen/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/TomRhodan/penguin-citizen</url>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Dashboard with RSI news, server status and shader cache overview</caption>
      <image>https://penguincitizen.de/assets/screenshots/dashboard.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Environment management for LIVE, PTU, EPTU and HOTFIX</caption>
      <image>https://penguincitizen.de/assets/screenshots/environments.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Launch page with performance options and runner selection</caption>
      <image>https://penguincitizen.de/assets/screenshots/launch.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Settings: paths, runners, environment variables and GitHub token</caption>
      <image>https://penguincitizen.de/assets/screenshots/settings.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>System check with guided fixes for Linux compatibility issues</caption>
      <image>https://penguincitizen.de/assets/screenshots/system-check.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <categories>
    <category>Utility</category>
    <category>Game</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>star citizen</keyword>
    <keyword>wine</keyword>
    <keyword>proton</keyword>
    <keyword>launcher</keyword>
    <keyword>rsi</keyword>
    <keyword>game</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#5b8def</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#1d2740</color>
  </branding>

  <supports>
    <control>pointing</control>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>touch</control>
    <control>gamepad</control>
  </supports>

  <recommends>
    <display_length compare="ge">900</display_length>
  </recommends>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.5.4" date="2026-05-01">
      <description>
        <p>Compare-with-SC panel that diffs saved settings against the live game state. Mode-aware joystick tuning dialog. ~70 new graphics, audio, combat and tracking settings exposed in the editor. Two-row binding pills. Many fixes around actionmaps.xml diffing, profile status, and binding mutations.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.3" date="2026-04-26">
      <description>
        <p>Data.p4k recycling between environments (copy, move, symlink). German localization variants Hybrid and Full with optional Blueprint integration. HOTFIX support for translations. Restored the joystick tuning editor. New helper scripts dev.sh and sc.sh.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.2" date="2026-04-12">
      <description>
        <p>Shader cache management dashboard widget for SC and DXVK with one-click clearing. Launch page shader warning when the cache is missing.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.1" date="2026-04-09">
      <description>
        <p>Security hardening: 0o600 config file permissions, winetricks integrity verification with pinned tag and SHA-256, stricter Wine PID validation, GitHub rate-limit handling. Memory leak fix in the gamepad subsystem.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
